听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我现在想和大家讨论的是线性一致性模型
I would now like to talk about a consistency model called linearizability.
我们前面看到的两阶段提交和原子提交
So, what we've seen so far with two-phase commit and atomic commitment is
都是面对崩溃的一致性保证
ensuring consistency in the face of crashes.
这些协议保证即使有节点崩溃
So, ensuring that even if nodes crash,
所有节点都会一起提交或中止一个事务
all of the nodes will either commit or abort a transaction.
我们在面对并发时也会考虑一致性问题
But we also have to worry about consistency in the face of concurrency.
如果多个节点并发读取或写入一些数据
So, what if multiple nodes are concurrently reading and writing some data,
我们如何使这些操作互相之间
how do we ensure those operations are consistent with each other
满足某种定义下的一致性保证
for some definition of consistency.
这就是线性一致性的含义
And this is what linearizability is about.
线性一致性是一个专门面向并发系统的一致性定义
So, it's one particular definition of consistency for concurrent systems.
是目前被广泛使用的最强一致性模型
And it is the strongest such model that is in widespread use.
线性一致性背后的基本思想是
And the idea behind linearizability is that
系统作为一个整体 其行为看起来好像不是一个复制系统或分布式系统
the system as a whole behaves as if it was not replicated or distributed at all.
系统看起来好像只有一份数据拷贝
So, it behaves as if there was actually only a single copy of the data,
且对于这份数据拷贝的所有操作都是原子性的
and all of the operations happen atomically on that single copy of the data.
当你提交一个读或写操作时
So, when you issue a read or write operation,
此操作将在某个时刻在满足原子性要求的条件下生效
that operation will take effect atomically at some point in time.
即使系统存在多个副本
And even though there might be multiple replicas in the system,
但站在客户端的角度看
from the point of view of the clients,
系统好像只有一份数据拷贝
it looks as though there was only a single copy of the data.
这个定义非常友好 很容易面向这一定义来实现系统
So, this is very nice, because it's easy to program against,
这个定义把分布式系统的所有复杂性
because it kind of reduces the all of the distributed systems complexity
归约到一个非常漂亮、描述简单、易于理解的定义
down to something which is very nice and manageable and small,
即系统好像只有一份数据拷贝
like a single copy of the data.
线性一致性定义的效果是
A consequence of this definition of linearizability is that
当你读取某个数据时 系统会保证你得到的一定是最新的值
whenever you read some data, you're guaranteed to get an up-to-date value
我们稍后就会看到如何定义最新的值
for some definition of up-to-date that we will see in a moment.
有时也把这一性质称为强一致性
And this is sometimes also called strong consistency.
但强一致性这个术语的定义有点模糊、也有点混乱
But the term strong consistency is a bit poorly defined. It's a bit vague and hand-wavy.
我们主要考虑线性一致性 这是一致性的一种形式化定义
So, we're going to stick with linearizability, which is formally defined.
我们在本课程中不会详细讨论线性一致性的形式化定义
We will not go into the exact formal definition in this course.
我只会通过一些例子向大家介绍线性一致性的直观思想
I'm just going to give you the intuition behind linearizability through some examples.
有趣的是 线性一致性不仅对于分布式系统来说非常重要
Interestingly, linearizability is not only important in distributed systems,
单计算机下的共享内存并发操作
but it actually is used also in the context of
也会用到线性一致性
shared-memory concurrency on a single computer.
原因在于 如果你有多个CPU核
And the reason there is that if you have multiple CPU cores,
每个CPU核都会有自己的缓存
then actually each CPU core has its own memory caches.
如果线程在两个不同的CPU核下运行
And if you have threads running on two different CPU cores,
可能有一个线程会将数据写入内存 此时写入数据会从CPU的缓存中写入
you might have one thread writing a value to memory, which actually goes to its cache,
随后 另一个线程正在读取内存相同位置下的数据
and then, a different thread reading that same location in memory,
这个线程此时可能无法看到第一个线程写入的数据
and it might not see the value that was written by the first thread,
因为这个线程的CPU缓存还没有更新这个数据的值
because its cache hasn't yet been updated with that value.
因此 即使只考虑单计算机
And so, within the scope of a single computer,
单计算机也可能会出现与复制系统类似的行为
you get this similar kind of behavior as in a replicated system,
因为不同级别缓存之间的行为与复制系统有些类似
because these different levels of caches give you something quite like replication.
这很有趣 因为线性一致性是分布式系统中的思想
I think this is interesting, because we're taking now this idea from distributed systems,
而单计算机的行为也开始和分布式系统有些相似了
and a single computer starts actually behaving a little bit like a distributed system too.
另一个需要注意的术语是
Another piece of terminology just to be careful of is
线性一致性和可串行化是两个不同的概念
linearizability and serializability are not the same thing.
虽然这两个概念对应的英文单词看起来有点像 但它们的含义完全不同
Even though the words look kind of similar, but they mean totally different things.
可串行化指的是事务之间的一种隔离形式
So, serializability is a form of isolation between transactions.
可串行化指的是 事务的执行效果
It's about transactions having the same effect
就像是在按照某种顺序串行执行
as if they were executed in some serial order.
线性一致性指的是多个副本的行为看起来好像只存在单一副本一样
Linearizability is around multiple replicas behaving as if there was a single replica.
因此 这是完全不同的两个概念
So, they're very different things.
为了让大家体会到线性一致性究竟是什么意思
OK, so, in order to give you a sense of what linearizability means,
我们要回顾之前课程中介绍过的一个概念
I'm going to go back to something we saw in a previous lecture,
即写后读一致性
which is read-after-write consistency.
回顾一下我们之前讨论过的知识点
So, if you remember what we discussed back then,
写后读一致性是在读写quorum的上下文中定义的
this was in the context of read and write quorums.
如果你有一个客户端 它想向某个对象x中写入某个值v_1
So, if you have a client that wants to write some value v_1 to some object x,
它可以把写入请求发送给quorum副本
it can make this write request to a quorum of replicas.
如果quorum返回OK 则set（设置）请求执行成功
If a quorum responds OK, then this set request is successful.
随后 相同的客户端想执行一次get（获得）请求
And then, subsequently, that same client might make a get requests,
它将get请求发送给quorum副本 得到一些响应
and send that get request to a quorum of replicas, get some responses back,
它使用时间戳来判断请求中的哪个值是最新值
use the timestamps to figure out which is the more recent value in the responses,
并让get请求返回这个最新值
and return that value from the get request.
我这里引入了一个新的表示符号
So, what is new here in this notation is now
这些方块表示执行特定操作的持续时间
I've got these boxes which indicate the execution time of this particular operation.
当操作开始时 我们先发送出这些请求
So, when the operation begins, we start by sending out these requests.
当收到quorum响应后
And then after a quorum of responses have been received,
我们宣布操作完成
we declare the operation to be finished.
因此 这些方块
So, the box here, this rectangle
表示客户端视角下操作的持续时间
shows the duration of the operation from the client's point of view.
现在 我们可以抽象具体的处理过程
Now, we can actually abstract away
忽略所有的内部状态、所有的通信消息、以及所有的副本
all of the internals, and this message communication, and all of the replicas.
我们可以只根据客户端看到的内容来定义一致性模型
And we can define a consistency model purely in terms of what the client sees,
也就是说 只站在客户端的视角来定义一致性模型
so, looking at things only from the client's point of view.
这会带来很大的帮助 因为这意味着我们的一致性模型
And this is useful, because it means our consistency model
不与系统的任何特定实现相绑定
is now not tied to one particular implementation of a system,
不与任何特定的分布式算法相绑定
or one particular distributed algorithm.
我们可以只站在客户端的视角来定义行为
We can define the behavior only from the client's point of view,
不考虑系统的内部是如何实现的
regardless of how the internals of this system are implemented.
每个操作内部
And so, within the execution of each operation,
可能会涉及多个消息的发送和接收过程
there might be multiple messages sent and received.
我们并不关心这些消息到底是什么
And we don't care particularly what those messages are exactly.
我们真正关心的是
What we do care about here is that
set操作完成后的get操作
this get operation here started after the set operation finished.
这两个操作存在时间依赖关系
So, there's this time dependence here
即get操作会在set操作之后发生
that the get operation happened later in time than the set operation.
因此 我们期望get操作看到的x的值
And therefore, we would expect the get operation to see a value of x
要至少等于最近一次set操作所设置的值
that is at least as recent as the value that was written by the previous set operation.
我们可以把这一时间依赖关系泛化
And we can generalize this timing dependency
不仅考虑一个客户端节点 而是考虑多个客户端节点
to be not just on a single node, but actually across multiple nodes.
这里我们有了客户端2
So, we could have the client 2 here,
客户端2
which starts a get operation
在另一个不同的客户端执行set操作后的某一时刻开始了get操作
sometime later in time after the set operation by a different client has completed.
这里同样存在实时依赖关系
And again, we have this real-time dependency here.
在线性一致性下 我们期望
So, under linearizability, we expect that
客户端2也可以看到最新的v_1
this client 2 will also see the up-to-date value v_1,
因为当我们只有单个数据拷贝时 所有操作都满足原子性
because that's the behavior we would get if we have a single copy of the data
我们就应该能得到最新的值
on which all of the operations are atomic.
这里的时间依赖关系看起来有点像此前发生关系
Now, this timing dependency here, it looks like the happens-before relationship,
但时间依赖关系与我们在前面课程中讨论的此前发生关系并不一样
but it is not the same as happens-before as we discussed in previous lectures.
回忆一下 我们是在消息发送和接收的场景下
So, if you remember, the way happens-before is defined is
定义的此前发生关系
it's defined in terms of sending and receiving messages.
如果在消息发送和接收图中存在某个路径
So, if there is some path through our message send and receive graph
使得你可以从一个事件流转到另一个事件
so that you can get from one event to the other event,
则我们称一个事件在另一个事件之前发生
then we have that one event happens before the other event.
此前发生关系并不是在实时场景下定义的
So, happens-before is not defined in terms of real-time,
而是在消息发送和接收的场景下定义的
it's defined in terms of message sending and receiving,
而线性一致性是在实时场景下定义的
whereas linearizability is defined in terms of real-time.
我们假设存在某个假想的观察者
So, we are assuming if there is some hypothetical observer
观察者可以看到操作何时结束、操作何时开始
who can see exactly when which operation finished and when which operation started,
观察者可以告诉我们
this observer can tell us
某个特定的操作是否在另一个操作之后发生
whether a certain operation started after another operation finished.
如果在之后发生 那么此操作就应该能观察到最新的状态
And therefore, it should be able to observe its up-to-date state.
即使节点之间没有相互通信 此种时间依赖关系仍然存在
And we have that dependency even if those nodes did not communicate.
即使客户端1没有给客户端2发送任何消息
So, even here, client 1 might not send a message to client 2 at all,
两个操作之间仍然存在实时时间依赖关系
but nevertheless, we have this real-time timing dependency between the two operations,
因为客户端2的操作
because this operation by client 2
一定发生在客户端1的操作之后
definitely happened later in time than client 1’s operation.
另一方面 如果两个操作的发生时间存在重叠
On the other hand, if the two operations overlap in real time,
则两个操作的可以按照任意顺序生效
then they can take effect in either order.
举例来说 在图中所示的情况下
So, in this case, here for example,
首先 set操作生效
we might have the set operation taking effect first,
随后 get操作生效
and then, the get operation taking effect second,
这种情况下 get操作将返回v_1
in which case, the get operation will return the value v_1.
但也有可能反过来
But it could just as well be the other way round.
也可能是get操作先生效 set操作后生效
So, it could be that the get operation takes effect first, the set operation second,
这两种行为都满足线性一致性
and both of these two behaviors are absolutely fine under linearizability,
因为线性一致性只是说
so, because linearizability just says that
操作生效的时间
the time when an operation takes effect
一定在操作开始后和操作结束前之间的某一时刻
must be some time after it started and before the operation finished.
也就是说 操作会在方块之间的某个位置
So, somewhere within this rectangle has to be the moment in time
在满足原子性的条件下生效
when the operation takes effect atomically,
但我们不知道生效时间具体在方块中的哪个位置
but we don't know where exactly within this rectangle,
因为我们无法准确知道网络的延时情况
because we don't know what the exact network latency is going to be.
在两个操作发生时间存在重叠的情况下
And so, in this particular case, where two operations overlap in time,
操作可以按照任意顺序生效
they can be ordered either way.
但如果操作发生时间不存在重叠 一个操作在另一个操作开始前就结束了
But if they do not overlap in time, so one operation finished before the other one started,
则在线性一致性下我们要求操作满足时间依赖关系
then we have this timing dependency under linearizability
从而告诉我们读取到的值必须是什么
that tells us what value we must read.
我们讨论过读后写一致性
So, we talked about read-after-write consistency,
可以通过quorum写和quorum读来保证读后写一致性
and that is ensured using quorum writes and quorum reads.
你可能会问
And you might wonder
使用quorum读和quorum写是否就足以保证系统满足线性一致性了
if those quorum reads and writes are sufficient in order to ensure linearizability.
有趣的是 答案是否定的
And the answer is no, interestingly.
只使用quorum读和quorum写无法保证系统满足线性一致性
It is not sufficient to ensure a linearizability just to have these quorum reads and writes.
我将通过一个例子来为大家讲解为什么无法保证线性一致性
And I'm going to show you with an example why that is the case.
在这个例子中 客户端1先有了一个set操作
So, in this example, here we have first of all a set operation by client 1.
和前面一样 客户端1想要把x的值设置为v_1
So, as before, client 1 wants to set the value of x to be v_1.
因此 它将set请求发送给所有三个副本
And so, it sends this set request to all three of the replicas.
我们这里假设 由于某种原因
And let's just assume for now that for some reason,
发送给副本A的请求很快就传输成功了
the request to replica A goes through very quickly,
但向B和C通信时 网络出现了延迟
but there's a network delay in communicating that request to B and C.
虽然B和C最终仍然能够得到更新的值v_1
So, eventually, B and C will get updated with the value v_1,
但目前只有副本A可以看到v_1
but right now, only replica A can see the value v_1,
因为网络出现了延迟
just because of the way the network happened to time things.
现在 客户端2开始提交get请求
Now, client 2 starts and makes a get request.
它向quorum请求x的值
And it requests the value of x from a quorum.
它从包含副本A和B的quorum得到响应
It gets a response from a quorum consisting of replicas A and B.
它像往常一样比较时间戳
And it's going to compare the timestamps as usual.
它会看到最新的值是v_1
And it's going to see that v_1 is the more up-to-date value.
因此 它会让get请求返回v_1
And so, it's going to return value v_1 from this get request.
接下来 客户端3来了 客户端3也想读取x的值
Next, client 3 comes along, and client 3 also wants to read the value of x.
它向节点发送一个get请求 它从quorum得到响应
It sends a get request to the nodes. It receives a quorum of responses.
此时 它从节点B和C得到了响应
In this case, it happens to get responses from nodes B and C.
这也是一个有效的quorum 没有任何问题
Now, this is also a valid quorum. So, this is fine.
但是B和C都还没有看到最新的v_1
But it happens that B and C, neither of them has seen that up-to-date value v_1 yet,
因为v_1仅到达了副本A 还没有到达B和C
because so far, value v_1 is only on replica A, but not on B and C.
因此 客户端3将只能看到v_0 它意识不到v_1的存在
So, client 3 is going to only see the value v_0. It is not a very aware of v_1.
两个get请求结束后 客户端1的set操作到达了副本B和C
Now, after this has happened, now client 1’s set operation reaches replicas B and C.
现在 副本B和C完成了更新并回复ok
So now, replicas B and C get updated and they respond ok.
所有请求都满足quorum条件
So, all of these requests here satisfy the quorum condition.
所有请求都获得了quorum节点的确认
So, all of them have acknowledgement from a quorum of nodes.
整个过程没有发生任何错误情况
And there are no errors happening here.
尽管如此 你可以看到
But nevertheless, you can see that
我们有两个get请求 两个请求分别来自客户端2和客户端3
we have these two get requests from client 2 and client 3.
这两个请求存在实时依赖关系
And we have a real-time dependency between these two requests,
因为客户端3的请求是在客户端2请求结束后开始的
because client 3's requests started later than client 2's requests finished.
因此 这两个操作存在实时依赖关系
So, as before, we have this real-time dependency between these two operations.
线性一致性不仅要考虑set和get操作的依赖关系
And linearizability is not only about this dependency between set and get operations,
也要考虑一个get操作与另一个get操作之间的依赖关系
but also from one get operation to another get operation.
和之前一样 我们期望系统满足线性一致性
And so, as before, we would expect here, under linearizability,
我们期望客户端3读到的值也和客户端2读到的值一样 都是最新的值
we would expect client 3 to read a value that is no older than the value read by client 2.
我们期望这里返回的是v_1 但实际上这里返回的是v_0
So, we expect this to return v_1 when in fact it returned v_0.
这违反了线性一致性
And so, this is a violation of linearizability.
现在 你可能会问 我们能修复这一问题吗？
Now, you might be wondering can we fix this.
我们能修复quorum读和quorum写算法
Can we fix this quorum read and write algorithm
使系统在任何情况下都满足线性一致性吗？
in order to make it linearizable under all circumstances?
答案是 是的 我们可以做到 具体方法描述如下
And the answer is yes, we can do that. And it works like this.
首先 客户端1的set请求和之前的做法完全一样
So, first of all, the set operation from client 1 that's exactly the same as it was before.
此请求会被立即发送给A 但发送给B和C时遇到了延迟 这没什么问题
So, it gets sent immediately to A, and it's delayed on its way to B and C. That's fine.
接下来是客户端2 客户端2和之前一样发送一个get请求
And next, client 2. So, client 2, as before, sends a get request,
并从包含A和B的quorum处得到响应
gets back responses from a quorum consisting of A and B.
它根据时间戳判断v_1是更新的值
It decides that v_1 is the newer value based on the timestamp.
但现在 我们不立即返回v_1
But now, we don't just return v_1 immediately.
客户端2现在知道副本B拥有一个过期值
But client 2 now knows that replica B has an outdated value.
客户端2不知道副本C的值是什么
And client 2 doesn't know what the value on replica C is,
但那个值也可能是过期值
but it might be outdated as well.
因此 客户端2要做的是
And so, what client 2 is going to do is
他向所有尚未持有最新值的副本重新发送set请求
now it's going to resend the set request to any replicas that did not have the latest value.
这种情况下 客户端2要把v_1与响应的原始时间戳t_1发送给其他副本
So, in this case, it's going to send the value v_1 along with the original timestamp t_1.
它将把v_1和t_1发送给副本B和C
It's going to send that to replicas B and C.
它要等待至少一个副本响应此请求
And it's going to wait for at least one of them to respond.
在图中 客户端2等待两个副本响应此请求 但得到一个副本的响应就够了
In this case, it's waiting for both of them to respond, but one of them is enough.
如果两个副本中有一个副本响应了 则此时客户端2知道
So, if one of the two responds, now client 2 knows that
当get请求结束后
the value v_1 is present on a quorum of replicas
quorum副本就拥有了v_1
at the time when this get request finishes.
因为客户端2现在知道quorum副本拥有了v_1
And because client 2 now knows that the value v_1 is present on the quorum,
因此 任意从quorum返回值的get请求
therefore, any subsequent get request that gets values from a quorum
也将能得到最新的值
will also see that up-to-date value.
我在前面的一个课程中把这一过程叫做读修复
So, this is what I call read repair in a previous lecture.
这里 客户端承担了将更新后的值分发给其他副本的角色
So, that is the clients taking a role in distributing the updated value to the other replicas.
而且 客户端2在这里没有立刻从get请求中返回
And here, as long as the client 2 does not immediately return from the get request,
它必须等待 确认新的值已经到达quorum副本后
but it has to wait until it is sure that the new value has reached a quorum of replicas,
才返回get请求
then it's allowed to return.
我们在get请求中增加额外这轮读修复后
And if we do that additional round of read repair as part of a get request,
算法就满足线性一致性了
then the algorithm becomes linearizable.
最后 客户端1得到了其它副本的响应
So, in this case now, finally, we have the response going to client 1.
所有人都对结果表示满意
And in this case, everyone is happy.
这种情况下 算法将保证客户端能看到v_1
In this case, client 3 is going to see the value v_1. It's assured to see that.
此算法让get和set请求满足线性一致性
So, this gives us linearizability for get and set requests.
我们用quorum读和读修复来实现get请求
In this case, we do the get by doing a quorum read with read repair,
我们把读修复包含的set请求称为盲写
and a set request is what we might call a blind write.
无论对象的当前值是什么 我们都用这个set请求覆盖当前值
So, the set request just overwrites whatever the value of this object is.
这不是一个条件覆盖操作
It doesn't like conditionally overwrite it.
这是一个无条件覆盖操作 不考虑当前值是什么
It's just an unconditional overwrite its value with whatever the current value is,
直接执行覆盖操作
just overwrite it with a new value.
这个算法被称为ABD算法
And this algorithm here, it's called the ABD algorithm,
这个算法足以保证请求满足线性一致性
is enough to ensure linearizability of these requests.
然而 可能发生的一种情况是
However, what might happen is
如果多个客户端并发在相同的对象上执行写操作
if multiple clients are concurrently writing to the same object,
则写操作会相互覆盖
then those might overwrite each other.
写操作之间没有任何协调过程
So, there's no coordination between the writes.
我们确实能保证所有节点从所有副本中都能读到相同的值
We will be ensured that they all end up with the same value across all of the replicas,
但两个并发写入可能存在冲突
but you might have a conflict due to two concurrent writes.
另一个你可能想获得的是比较交换操作
So, one other thing you might want is a compare-and-swap operation.
在本课程前半部分的并发系统课程中我们讲到过
So, remember this again from the first half of this course on concurrent systems,
比较交换操作通常作为原子指令内置在CPU中
a compare-and-swap operation is often built into CPUs as an atomic instruction,
这个操作实现的功能是 仅当某个内存位置的旧值等于某个特定值时
which allows you to set the value of some memory location to some new value
才能在此内存上设置某个新的值
only if its old value is some particular value.
这个操作是原子性的
And it does this atomically.
即使多个线程
So, even if multiple threads
并发执行比较交换操作
are concurrently executing these compare-and-swap operations,
也只有一个线程才能写入成功
only one of them is going to succeed.
因此 比较交换操作不允许并发的上下文切换
So, it's not going to allow concurrent context switches
不允许并发检查旧值并设置新值
between like the checking of the old value and the setting of the new value.
你可能会问 分布式系统下能否做到这一点呢？
And you might wonder can we do the same thing?
我们能否在分布式系统下实现满足线性一致性的比较交换操作？
Can we do a linearizable compare-and-swap operation in a distributed system?
答案是 是的 我们能实现
And the answer is, actually, yes, we can.
但我们要使用
But we have to use a different algorithm
与quorum读和quorum写不一样的算法
from the quorum reads and writes that we just did.
我们需要再次使用全序关系广播
We can instead use total order broadcast again.
全序关系广播再一次发挥了作用
So, once again, total order broadcast comes to the rescue.
这个算法用一张幻灯片就能介绍完 非常简单
And this algorithm fits on just one slide. It's quite simple.
我们实现满足线性一致性的比较交换操作和get操作的方法
The way we can implement a linearizable compare-and-swap operation
就是使用全序关系广播
and a linearizable get operation is using total order broadcast.
如果我们想执行一个get操作 我们将构造格式为(get, x)的消息
If we want to do a get operation, we're going to make a message saying “get x”.
我们用全序关系广播将此消息发送给所有的节点
And we're going to total order broadcast that to all of the nodes.
我们不要立刻响应此消息
And we're not going to respond immediately.
我们要等待全序关系广播完成消息传递后再响应
We're going to wait for that message to be delivered by total order broadcast.
类似地 如果我们想原子性地执行一次比较交换操作
Likewise, if we want to do an atomic compare-and-swap operation,
我们将此操作打包成一条消息
we're just going to package that operation up as a message,
通过全序关系广播分发此条消息
distributed via total order broadcast,
等待消息完成传递
and wait for that message to be delivered.
当全序关系广播传递了一条get消息时
Now, when one of the get messages is delivered by total order broadcast,
回忆一下全序关系广播所做的事情
well, remember what total order broadcast does,
它会保证所有节点按照相同的顺序传递相同的消息
it just ensures delivery of the same messages in the same order.
因此 所有副本都会按照相同的顺序收到这些消息
So, therefore, all replicas are going to receive these messages in the same order.
因此 当get消息被传递时
So, therefore, here now, when that message is delivered,
我们只需要读取本地状态 读取x的值
we can just read the local state, read the value of x,
并把当前值作为get消息的返回值
and return that current value as the result of this get operation.
类似地 如果我们从全序关系广播收到一条CAS消息
And likewise, if we receive a CAS message
这里的CAS是比较交换的英文缩写
for compare-and-swap from total order broadcast,
我们只需要在本地直接执行比较交换算法
then we just do the straightforward compare-and-swap algorithm.
如果当前状态就是我们想要的旧值
So, if the existing state is the old value that we want,
我们就把旧值设置为新值 并把返回的success设置为true
then we set it to the new value and we return success being true.
否则 我们不做任何修改 把返回的success设置为false
Otherwise, we don't change anything and we return success being false.
我们把success作为比较交换操作的返回值
And we return this as the result of the compare-and-swap operation.
这个算法非常简单
And this is very simple,
因为全序关系广播本质上为我们提供了一个单线程视角
but because total order broadcast essentially gives us this kind of single-threaded view
所有节点会按照相同的全序关系传递所有的操作
that all of the operations are delivered in the same total order on all of the nodes.
我们这里得到的本质上与状态机复制相同
What we have here is essentially the same as state machine replication.
我们保证get操作可以从所有副本得到相同的结果
We are going to ensure that the get operations get the same result on each replica,
比较交换操作在每个副本得到相同的执行效果
and the compare-and-swap operations have the same effect on every replica.
这样一来 我们就得到了线性一致性
And so, here we get linearizability.
我们基于全序关系广播得到了满足线性一致性的操作
We get these linearizable operations by building on total order broadcast,
我认为这是一个非常干净、非常简洁的构造
which I think is a very neat construction.